Guide to the Henry Heald Speeches Collection 1952-1956 MC 50
New York University Archives
Henry Heald Speeches
1952-1956
MC 50
New York University Archives
0.75 linear feet
The Henry Heald Speeches Collection contains numerous addresses, interviews, and commencement speeches made by Henry T. Heald between 1952 and 1956, while he was Chancellor of NYU.
Heald, Henry T., (Henry Townly), 1904-1975
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangment
This collection is comprised of 107 folders organized chronologically into 3 boxes.
Biographical Note
Henry Townley Heald was born on November 8, 1904 in Lincoln Nebraska. He obtained his Bachelors in 1923 from Washington State University and went on to get his Masters degree in Civil Engineering from the University of Illinois. He went on to work at the Illinois Institute of Technology, eventually becoming President in 1938. Following his tenure there he came the Chancellor of NYU in 1950 where he helped strengthen the institution and became an outspoken proponent for evaluating and restructuring higher education with an outlook towards accessibility for all. In 1956, Heald became the President of the Ford Foundation where he channeled the Foundation's resources into philanthropic pursuits. During his ten years as President, the Ford Foundation gave 1.75 billion towards philanthropic purposes and established programs for the arts, the physical sciences, and engineering. Henry T. Heald died on November 23, 1975 in Winter Park, Florida.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Heald Speeches Collection contains over 100 separate speeches and addresses made by Henry T. Heald, all from between 1952 and 1956, when he was Chancellor at New York University. Included are addresses on the importance of higher education, the future of NYU, and the connection between education and freedom.
New York University. Chancellors.; New York University.; Engineering; Ford Foundation.; Interviews.; Radio addresses, debates, etc.; Speeches.
- Suggestions for the HTH Remarks at Catholic Dedication, Feb. 6, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- HTH Remarks, 64th Annual Dinner, NYU Law Alumni Assoc., Inc., Feb. 19, 1952. Waldorf-Astoria Grand Ballroom. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- HTH Remarks, Medical Center Dinner, Feb. 28, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- HTH Address at NYU Alumni Dinner, March 27, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- HTH, "Education's Challenge," Speech at Washington Award Dinner, April 21, 1952 - Chicago. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- HTH Address, American Foundation for Pharmaceutical Education, April 24, 1952 - New York City. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Address before Educational Alumnia Association, April 25, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- HTH Remarks, National Conference of Christian and Jews Dinner, Brotherhood Awards to John Foster Dulles and Samuel Daniel Leidesdorf, May 12, 1952; Waldorf. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- HTH Remarks of Welcome, Hall of Fame Ceremony -- Susan B. Anthony and Thomas Paine, May 18, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Excerpts from HTH's Address to the Medallion Group, May 22, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- HTH Installation Address, 120th Commencement, June 11, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- HTH, Interview on WOR Radio. Recorded June 9, 1952 for Broadcast 6 p.m., June 11, 1952., June 9-June 11, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- HTH Remarks, SMPTE Meeting, NYU, June 25, 1952. School of Education Auditorium. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- HTH Remarks, Summer Session Assembly, School of Education, July 3, 1952. Education Auditorium. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- HTH, "Science Looks Ahead," Remarks at Evening Engineering Graduation, July 15, 1952 Gould Library Auditorium, University Heights. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- HTH, Talk at the first meeting of the Mteropolitan Section, ASCE, for the 1952-1953 year. "The Engineer Becomes a University President," October 15, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- HTH, "New York University Looks Ahead," Radio Broadcast No. 1, WYNC. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- HTH, "Private Colleges and Universities Need Money," (Article in Challenge Magazine, October, 1952). (Box 1, Folder 18)
- HTH, "A Chance to Serve," Speech before New York Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, November 6, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- HTH Remarks, Cornerstone Ceremony -- Medical Center, November 7, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- HTH Remarks, RESA Initiation (Scientific Research Society of America), November 13, 1952, at George WAshington Hotel (Washington Room), New York. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- HTH, "The Volunteer in Education," Speech at Lane Bryant Award Luncheon, November 17, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- HTH Remarks at Dedication of the Wallace Clark Center for International Management. December 4, 1952. Lassman Hall, Commerce Building. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- HTH Radio Address, "NYU Serves the Community," Jan. 9, 1953 Broadcast No. 2 -- WYNC. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- HTH Talk, Clarkson College Alumni, January 10, 1952, Philadelphia, PA. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- HTH Address, "Education and Public Policy," January 19, 1953. Annual Meeting of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers, Hotel Statler, New York City (Press Release sent out January 16, 1953)., January 16 - 19, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- HTH Speech, "The Faculty Role in University Administration," Jan. 19, 1953, to School of Education Faculty -- NYU. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- HTH Address, "Our Community Responsibility," before Protestant Council of Churches, January 26, 1953 -- New York City. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- HTH Address, "The Challenge of the 1960's: Today's Children Reach College Age," February 14, 1953. Barnard forum, Waldorf - Astoria Hotel. (Box 1, Folder 29)
- HTH Address, "Education and Freedom," Feb. 22, 1953 at Rollins College. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- HTH Talk, University Club Luncheon, March 21, 1953., March 21, 2953 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- HTH Address, "The University in an Urban Community," April 14, 1953 at the East Side Forum, New York City. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- HTH Remarks, Dental Alumni Dinner, April 24, 1953, Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- HTH Remarks, "Report on the University," June 4, 1953 Medical Alumni Dinner, Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. (Box 1, Folder 34)
- HTH Remarks, COUNCIL Dinner, Hotel Pierre, June 9, 1953. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- HTH, "Commencement Welcome," New York University, June 10, 1953, University Heights. (Box 2, Folder 36)
- HTH, Commencement Address at Northwestern University, June 15, 1953. (Box 2, Folder 37)
- HTH Address, "Slum Prevention: A Public Necessity," before the Metropolitan Housing and Planning Council of Chicago, June 16, 1953. (Box 2, Folder 38)
- HTH Remarks, "You and the University," School of Education Convocation (for New Students and Parents), September 29, 1953. Education Auditorium., Sept. 29, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- HTH Remarks, United Nations Dinner, Oct. 6, 1953, Delegates Dining Room -- UN. (Box 2, Folder 40)
- HTH Talk, "A Task for Volunteers," October 14, 1953, at the Annual YWCA Lunchon, Plaza Hotel. (Box 2, Folder 41)
- HTH Remarks, Annual Engineers Dinner -- ECPD -- October 16, 1953. (Box 2, Folder 42)
- HTH Remarks, Military Science Building Cornerstone Ceremony, Nov. 4, 1953. University Heights Campus. (Box 2, Folder 43)
- HTH Talk, "The Citizen's Part," November 5, 1953, before the New York Tuberculosis and Health Association Annual Conference, in New York. (Box 2, Folder 44)
- HTH Address, "Purposes of the Conference -- As Seen By the Educator," Nov. 12, 1953 Industry - College Conference, White Sulphur Springs, W. VA. (Box 2, Folder 45)
- HTH Talk, "Unity in Diversity," Nov. 27, 1953, at the annual meeting of the Middle States Association, Atlantic City, New Jersey. (Box 2, Folder 46)
- HTH Talk, "The Volunteer Layman", YMCA Report Luncheon, January 8, 1954, Hotel Commodore, New York. (Box 2, Folder 47)
- HTH Statement, on the Proposed Washington Square Southeast Redevelopment Project. Board of Estimate Hearing, January 26, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 48)
- HTH Remarks, Freshman Orientation, February 3, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 49)
- HTH Remarks (for recording), Nothern California Alumni Club, April 6, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 50)
- HTH Remarks, WSC Faculty Meeting, April 6, 1954 (On Liberal Arts, University, Etc.). (Box 2, Folder 51)
- HTH Address, " The Responsibility of the Professions to the Future Society," April 9, 1954 in Albany, New York, during the 170th Anniversary Convocation of the Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York. (Box 2, Folder 52)
- HTH Address, "Pattern of Progress," April 29, 1954 to American Society of Tool Engineers, Philadelphia. (Speech not delivered due to death of HTH's Father). (Box 2, Folder 53)
- HTH Address, "The Urban Institution in Higher Education," May 15, 1954, at the inauguration of Dr. Francis H. Horn as President of Pratt Institute, Brooklyn, New York. (Box 2, Folder 54)
- HTH Remarks, WATV, June 7, 1954 (on University, Higher Education). (Box 2, Folder 55)
- HTH Remarks, NYU Commencement, June 9, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 56)
- HTH Commencement Address, "Means and Ends," at Newark, College of Engineering June 10, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 57)
- HTH Remarks, Dedication of Riverdale Temple, New York City, September 19, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 58)
- HTH Address, "The Next 25 Years in the New York Metropolitan Region," before New York University Regional Plan Association, Oct. 6, 1954., October 6, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- HTH Remarks, University Heights, Chapel Exercises, Oct. 7, 1954 -- Not Used., October 7, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- HTH Remarks, Opening Centiennial Convocation of NYU's College of Engineering at the University Heights Campus, Oct. 12, 1954., October 12, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 61)
- HTH Remarks, Annual dinner -- American Council on Education, October 14, 1954., Oct. 14, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 62)
- HTH Address, "Education for Safe Living," October 18, 1954, before National Safety Council, Chicago, Illinois. (Box 2, Folder 63)
- HTH Address, Association of American Medical Colleges, October 19, 1954. French Lick, Indiana. (Box 2, Folder 64)
- HTH Remarks, Gould Center Dedication (Student Center) October 30, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 65)
- HTH Speech, "A Trustee's Responsiblity," Nov. 16, 1954. Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions. (Box 2, Folder 66)
- HTH Remarks, Institution of Mathematical Sciences, NYU, Nov. 29, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 67)
- HTH Remarks, Jewish Culture Foundation Dinner for Moss and Hornstein, Dec. 9, 1954. Waldorf, Starlight Room, New York City. (Box 2, Folder 68)
- HTH Welcoming Remarks, Modern Language Association, Dec. 28, 1954, Hotel Statler, New York City. (Box 2, Folder 69)
- HTH Remarks, "An Appreciation of Franklin," Jan. 17, 1955. Biltmore Hotel, New York. (Box 2, Folder 70)
- HTH Remarks, Midwinter Convocation -- College of Engineering, January 29, 1955, University Heights. (Box 3, Folder 71)
- HTH Address, "Every Age is an Age of Crisis," North Central Association, Chicago, Illinois, March 25, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 72)
- HTH Remarks, Foreign Language Conference, April 1, 1955. Hotel new Yorker, New York City. (Box 3, Folder 73)
- HTH Address, "The Second Mile," April 25, 1955, Greater Nwe York Fund. (Box 3, Folder 74)
- HTH Remarks, National Asosciation of Education buyers -- New York, May 2, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 75)
- HTH Remarks, Overseas Information conference at NYU, May 6, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 76)
- HTH Remarks, Alumni Federation Farewell dinner for DD Henry, Ambassador Hotel, New York, May 10, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 77)
- HTH Remarks, Commencement -- Nursing Graduates of St. Luke's Hospital, New York city, May 18, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 78)
- HTH, "Pathways to Progress," commencement Address at the University of Wichita, May 29, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 79)
- HTh Statement, at Dedication of Loew Dormitory, University Heights center, October 8, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 80)
- HTH Remarks, Christ Church Annual Dinner, November 7, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 81)
- HTH Remarks as Chairman, first General Session -- Building for Brotherhood Dedication Program, November 9, 1955, Waldorf-Astoria -- West Ballroom, New York. (Box 3, Folder 82)
- HTH Remarks, "Why New York?," Wayfarer's Club, Chicago, November 22, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 83)
- HTH, Welcoming Remarks, Commerce Dean's Day, December 2, 1955., December 3, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 84)
- HTH Remarks, National Conference of Christians and Jews, Waldorf Dinner, December 7, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 85)
- HTH Remarks, Luncheon Meeting of the Municipal Forum of New York, February 9, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 86)
- HTH Remarks, New School for Social Research, New York city, Cornerstone Laying, February 11, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 87)
- HTH Remarks, Congregation of B'Nai Jeshurun, New York City, February 19, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 88)
- HTH Remarks, "Role of a Law Center in a University," March 12, 1956, at Law-Alumni Dinner. (Box 3, Folder 89)
- HTH Remarks, Arts and Engineering Alumni Meeting, University heights, March 15, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 90)
- HTH Remarks, Beth Israel Hospital School of Nursing Graduation, New York City, March 20, 1956. (Box 3, File 91)
- HTH Remarks, "Youth: America's Most Vital Asset," Jewish Welfare board Biennial convention, April 5, 1956, New York City. (Box 3, Folder 92)
- HTH Introduction of French Ambassador, April 6, 1956, Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, New York. (Box 3, Folder 93)
- HTH, "An Educator Looks at Industry," April 17, 1956, Industry-Education Conference, Hofstra College. (Box 3, Folder 94)
- HTH Remarks, Westchester Science Fair, April 20, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 95)
- HTH Remarks, for Tau Beta Pi, April 21, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 96)
- HTH Remarks, Times Square Club Honoring Roy E. Larsen, April 29, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 97)
- HTH Outline, Management Club Talk, May 4, 1956, NYU. (Box 3, Folder 98)
- HTH Remarks, Alumni Medallion Dinner, May 17, 1956 Faculty club - NYU. (Box 3, Folder 99)
- HTH Remarks, Hall of Fame Ceremonies -- Woodrow Wilson Bust, May 20, 1956, University Heights. (Box 3, Folder 100)
- HTH Remarks, "Kimball the Kollector," May 22, 1956 - Kimball Dinner. (Box 3, Folder 101)
- HTH, "You Win By Losing," Commencement Address, Duke University, June 4, 1956, Durham, North Carolina. (Box 3, Folder 102)
- HTH, NYU Commencement, June 6, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 103)
- HTH Remarks, "Can We Meet the Challenge of Universal Education?," June 9, 1956, Western Michigan College, Kalamazoo, Michigan. (Box 3, Folder 104)
- HTH Remarks, "Who Is Responsible for Education?," June 13, 1956, Commencement -- University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA. (Box 3, Folder 105)
- HTH Remarks, "Can We Meet the Challenge of Universal Education?," June 14, 1956, Commencement - New Jersey State Teachers College, Newark, New Jersey. (Box 3, Folder 106)
- HTH Talk at Harvard, "Satisfactions of a College Presidency -- If Any," June 20, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 107)